Guide to the Charles Loewner Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Charles Loewner papers
1919-1990
SC0104
Charles Loewner
4.5 Linear feet
Professional records include lecture notes, course material, manuscripts, research notes, writings; personal papers include academic records, correspondence, clippings, photographs, and publishing contracts created and maintained by Charles Loewner, a world-renowned mathematician and Professor Emeritus at Stanford University from 1951-1968.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, Mathematics Library, 1972; Gift of Marian Tracy, 2007.
Information about Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Biography / Administrative History
Professor Emeritus Charles Loewner was born on May 29, 1893, in the village of Lany, near Prague, which was at the time the capital of Bohemia. Loewner received his Ph.D. in Mathematics at the Prague University. From 1922-1928 he taught at Friedrich Wilhelm University in Berlin. Following a brief lectureship at Cologne, he was appointed to a chair in Mathematics at the German Charles University in Prague. The occupation of Czechoslovakia in 1939 prompted his emigration to the United States. He taught at Louisville, Brown, and Syracuse University prior to his appointment in 1951 as Professor of Mathematics at Stanford University, where he specialized in complex analysis and differential geometry. Loewner remained at Stanford University until his death in 1968.
Scope and Content of Collection
The first seven boxes of this collection consist largely of Loewner's lectures notes, 1923-1956, with some exams and class projects; manuscripts and typescripts of articles, 1919-62, including his 1933 thesis; and research notes and writings. Subjects of his writings and research include differential equations, matrices, and semigroups. Other items include several articles by other mathematicians on Loewner's work, note cards, and a small amount of correspondence.
Accession 2007-257 consists of Loewner's personal papers, which are comprised of correspondence pertaining to his emigration to the United States during World War II, his wartime employment search, and attempts to determine the whereabouts of his family remaining in Europe. This accession also contains Loewner's personal academic records, and correspondence to and from colleagues at the many academic institutions where Loewner taught including the University of Louisville, Brown University, Syracuse University, and Stanford University. Other items include photographs, publishing contracts, memorial tributes to Loewner and his wife Elizabeth, and news clippings about the Loewner family.
Access Terms
Loewner, Charles, 1893-1968.; Stanford University. Department of Mathematics. Faculty.; Differential equations.; Mathematics--Study and teaching.; Matrices.; Semigroups.
Collection Contents
- Original Accession, Series 1; 7 box(es)
  - Class Materials
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes (in German), 1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes (in German), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes (in German), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Notebook, mathematics lecture notes, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Mathematics lecture notes, Math 212, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Mathematics examination programs, miscellaneous classes, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Notebooks, mathematics lecture notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Problem seminar, notes and student work, circa 1953-1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Notes for seminar on order properties in mathematics, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Exams, miscellaneous, 1957-1958 and undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Class project, "Continuous Groups,", undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Class project, Math 220 A,B pages 1-93, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Class project, Math 220 A,B pages 94-201, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Class project, Math 220 A,B pages 202-end, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Notes on complex variables (not in Loewner's hand but possibly from his lectures), undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence
    - Mitchell, Josephine, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Pick, George (in German), 1936 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Manuscripts and Typescripts by Loewner
    - "Approximation on a real interval by polynomials with restricted zeroes" (written with J. Korevaar), 1962 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Baecklund's transformation theory of partial differential equations and fluid flow, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Baecklund's transformation theory of partial differential equations and fluid flow, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Conservation laws in compressible fluid flow and associated mappings,", undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Conservation laws of certain systems of partial differential equations and associated mappings,", undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Determination of the critical exponent of the Green's function,", undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "Generation of solutions of systems of partial differential equations by composition of infinitesimal Baecklund transformations,", circa 1952 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "A group theoretical characterization of some manifold structures,", undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Integral operators, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Introduction [semigroups and non-Euclidean geometry], undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "Monotonic and convex functions of higher order in arbitrary manifolds,", undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Monotonic functions of arbitrary order, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "On generation of solutions of the biharmonic equation in the plane by conformal mappings,", undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "On generation of solutions of the biharmonic equation in the plane by conformal mappings,", undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "On pairs of quadratic forms in Hilbert space,", 1945 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "On some classes of functions associated with line congruences and partial differential equations of first order,", undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - "On some transformation semigroups,", circa 1956 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - "On the conformal capacity in space,", undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Riemann surfaces of infinite genus, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - "Semigroup of Conformal Mappings" [mss], undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - "Semigroup of Conformal Mappings" [tss], 1957 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Semigroups, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Semigroups, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Semigroups-miscellaneous pages and bibliography, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Semigroups-incomplete papers and miscellany, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "Some classes of functions defined by difference or differential inequalities,", undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "Spektraltheorie linearer operatoren," Prag, pp. 1-100, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - "Spektraltheorie linearer operatoren," Prag, pp. 101-200, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - "Spektraltheorie linearer operatoren," Prag, pp. 201-300, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - "Spektraltheorie linearer operatoren," Prag, pp. 301-395, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - "Spektraltheorie linearer operatoren," Prag, miscellaneous pages, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - "A theorem on the partial order derived from a certain transformation semigroup," [with additional notes], 1959 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Transformation semigroups, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "A Transformation theory of the partial differential equation of gas dynamics,", undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "Ueber monotone Matrixfunktionen" [written in Prague], 1930s (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - "Valueless vane diffusor with an arbitrary vane shape,", undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Typescripts, incomplete, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Typescripts, miscellaneous and fragmentary, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lectures
    - Comparison of European and American universities, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Partial differential equations and fluid flow in a plane, circa 1953 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Monotonic functions, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous lecture notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Research Notes and Writings by Loewner
    - Notebook (in German), undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous notes (in German), undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Baecklund, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - B II, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - B. T. III, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Capacity, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Conservation laws, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Conservation laws III, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Distortion Tl, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Moebius transformations, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - P.D.E., undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Partial d.e. in the r-s-t space, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Positive matrices, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Project research, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Scalar function of matrices, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Sequence of functions, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - S-group and convex domains, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Semigroup theoretical considerations, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Some semigroups of linear operators, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Symmetrization of functions, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Transformation semigroup, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - U.P. I, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - U.P. II, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - U.P. III, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Viscous fluids, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Unlabeled 1, Summer 1957 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Unlabeled 2, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Unlabeled 3, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Unlabeled 4, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Unlabeled 5, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Unlabeled 6, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Unlabeled 7, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Unlabeled 8, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Unlabeled 9, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Unlabeled 10, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Unlabeled 11, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Unlabeled 12, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Unlabeled 13, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Proposals, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous items, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Works by Others
    - Donoghue, W. F. "The Theorems of Loewner and Pick" [tss], reprint, and correspondence, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Yanikowski, Y. "Methode algebrique et equation de Löwner" [tss], undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Reprints of articles about Loewner's work by Ch. Pommerenke, E. L. Whitney, Izydor Dziubinski, and M. Pinl, 1958-1967 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Duff, G. F. D. and R. A. Ross, "Indefinite Green's functions and elementary solutions" [tss] with letter to Loewner in German, possibly from a reviewer of this article, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Wigner, Eugene P. and Mutsuo M. Yanase, three articles, undated (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - "Matrix differential equations," manuscript possibly by C. S. Ballantine, undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Notes on temperature distribution in a slab of two layers, possibly by G. R. Stibitz, undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - German reprint, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous Items
    - Loewner, "Der Lichtdruck," Prag, 10 January 1919 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Notebook of Hans Freudenthal (in German), undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Notes on bounds for the eigenvalue, not in Loewner's hand, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Advanced Matric Theory, lectures by Charles Loewner, notes by C. S. Ballantine, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Notecards on mathematical problems, definitions, etc., undated (Box 7, Folder Not Foldered)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2007-257; 2 box(es)
  - Academic Records-Report Cards, 1905-1910 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Academic Records-Report Cards, 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic Records-Report Cards, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Academic Records-Report Cards, 1916-1917, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Academic Records-Correspondence-Deutschen Technischen Hochschule & Karl Ferdinands-Universität (Prague), 1918, 1920-1922 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Academic Records-Correspondence-Deutsche Univerität (Prague), 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Personal Correspondence (Family), 1934, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Personal Correspondence (Family), (folder 1 of 2), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Personal Correspondence (Family), (folder 2 of 2), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal Correspondence (Family), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal Correspondence (Family), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Personal Correspondence (Including correspondence to Loewner's family after his death), 1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Family Records (Miscellaneous), 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Emigration to America-Correspondence, 1933-1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Emigration to America-Correspondence & Curriculum Vitae, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Emigration to America-Correspondence (Testimonial by L.L. Silverman), 1931-1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Emigration to America-Correspondence (Testimonial by J.E. Littlewood), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Emigration to America-Correspondence (Testimonial by Harald Bohr), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Emigration to America-Correspondence & Testimonials, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Emigration to America-Correspondence from Society For the Protection of Science and Learning, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Emigration to America-Correspondence, Telegrams, and Affidavits Concerning Loewner's Family's Whereabouts, 1939-1944 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Emigration to America-Travel to America and Transfer of Effects to Louisville, KY, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence from "Selfhelp of Emigres from Central Europe, Inc.,", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Employment Offers, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Employment Search-Offers and Rejections, 1942-1950 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence-University of Louisville, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence-William Marshall Bullit (Louisville), 1944-1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence-Brown University, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence-Syracuse University (Professional), 1942-1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence-Syracuse University (Personal), 1941-1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence-Stanford University, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Political Correspondence-Lee Lorch, 1949-1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Political Correspondence-Lee Lorch, 1950-1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Political Correspondence-William A. Pierce, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Political Correspondence-Chandler Davis, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence-To/From Elizabeth Loewner, 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence-Miscellaneous, 1940-1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Publishing-Contracts & Correspondence, 1943-1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Publishing-Correspondence with M.I.T. Press, 1970, 1974-1975, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Publishing-Correspondence (Miscellaneous), 1979-1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Article Abstract by Loewner (Syracuse), 1947 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Documents (Lists), undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Elizabeth Loewner's Death, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Charles Loewner's Death, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - News Clippings, 1939-1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Concert Announcements-Elizabeth Loewner, undated & 1949 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Photographs, circa 1930s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Articles, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)